Rubin, Jay mss., 1912-1920 LMC 2571
Lilly Library
Rubin, Jay mss.
1984-2006
Lilly Library
Rubin, Jay, 1941-
LMC 2571
7 Boxes
The Rubin, Jay mss., 1984-2006, consist of the corespondence, papers, manuscripts, and typescripts related to literary translations from the Japanese by translator Jay Rubin.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Jay Rubin, 1941-, is one of the primary translators of Japanese novelist Haruki Murakami's works into English. He has also translated the work of a number of other Japanese authors and written a biographical literary analysis of Murakami.
Scope and Content Note
The Rubin, Jay mss., 1984-2006, consist of the corespondence, papers, manuscripts, and typescripts related to literary translations from the Japanese by translator Jay Rubin. The bulk of the collection relates to his translations of Haruki Murakami's work, though some papers relate to translations of other Japanese authors' works as well as Rubin's own writings.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 2006, 2007, 2010.
Literature--translating; Rubin, Jay, 1941-; Murakami, Haruki, 1949-; Natsume, Sōseki, 1867-1916; Sakaguchi, Ango, 1906-1955; Akutagawa, Ryūnosuke, 1892-1927
- I. TRANSLATIONS - MURAKAMI.
  Scope and Contents
  Relating to Rubin's translations of works by Haruki Murakami. Arranged by work following original order.
  - After Dark (Box 1)
    - Printer's manuscript - corrected, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Rough pages, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Edited typescript, 2007 (Box 3)
    - Edited page proofs, 2007 (Box 3)
  - "Another Way To Die" (Box 1)
    - Edited printout, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Blind Willow, Sleeping Woman (Box 1)
    - Harvill proofs, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Typescript, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Corrected page proofs, 2006; (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Corrected typescript, 2005; (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Page proofs, 2006; (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Edited page proofs, 2006; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - The Elephant Vanishes (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, corrections, and manuscript, 1992; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - The Wind-Up Bird Chronicle (Box 1)
    - Correspondence re: translation, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Murakami revisions (pre-publication?), 1994 (Box 1)
    - Uncut Book 2 manuscript, Ch. 1-6, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Uncut Book 2 manuscript, Ch. 7-13, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Uncut Book 2 manuscript, Ch. 14-18, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Cut occurrences, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Murakami's cuts for vol. 1 and 2, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Uncut manuscript, n.d.; (6 folders) (Box 1)
    - Cut manuscript, title page-chapter 10, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Cut manuscript, n.d.; (5 folders) (Box 2)
    - First pass, 1997; (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - Pages with cuts, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Slightly revised version, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Dead matter, master rough pages, 1997; (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - Knopf - 'Blues', 1997 (Box 2)
    - Corrected typescript, 1997; (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Original serialized chapters, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Original serialized chapters, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Annotated typescript, n.d.; (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - Harvill Proofs - Correspondence with Victoria Millar, Book 1, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Harvill Proofs - Book 2, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Harvill Proofs - Book 3, 1998 (Box 6)
  - Birthday Stories (Box 4)
    - Corrected typescript and original text, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Norwegian Wood (Box 4)
    - Book I typescript, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Book II typescript, 2000; (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Book I galleys, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Book II galleys, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Notes on "Norway calendar" (Box 4)
    - Edited typescript, 1999; (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Corrected typescript, 2000; (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - First draft, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - "Tony Takitani" (Box 4)
    - Edits, 2002 (Box 4)
  - "Airplane" (Box 4)
    - Edits, 2002 (Box 4)
  - "Birthday Girl" (Box 4)
    - Edits, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Various Short Stories (Box 4)
    - Edits, 2000-2003 (Box 4)
  - "Seventh Man" (Box 4)
    - Edits and original text, 1998 (Box 4)
  - After the Quake (Box 4)
    - Original text and typescript (Box 4)
    - Edited typescript, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Corrected galleys, 2002 (Box 4)
- II. TRANSLATIONS - OTHER WRITERS.
  Related to Rubin's translations of authors other than Murakami. Arranged by work following original order.
  - Rashomon and Seventeen Other Stories (Box 4)
    - Corrections, original Japanese, 2005; (7 folders) (Box 6)
    - Corrected page proofs, 2005; (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Page proofs, 2005 (Box 6)
    - Proofs, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Typescript, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Page proofs, 2005 (Box 5)
  - The Miner (Box 7)
    - Corrections, 1987; (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Corrected pages sent to publisher, 1987 (Box 7)
    - Corrected proof, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - "In the Forest, Under Cherries in Full Bloom" (Box 7)
    - Manuscript and correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 7)
- III. WRITINGS.
  Arranged by work following original order.
  - Haruki Murakami and the Music of Words (Box 7)
    - Typescript, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Edited typescript, 1998; (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Original Japanese text, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Typescript, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Injurious to Public Morals (Box 7)
    - Manuscript, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Typescript, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Chronology and notes (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, photos, and reviews, 1980-1984 (Box 7)